A Guide to the Papers of John Dos Passos 1865-1998
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Personal (Box 122-139)
  - Awards (Box 122-125)
    - Civil War Centennial Commission 1966 (Box 122)
    - Converse College 1964 (Box 122)
    - Civil War Centennial Commission 1966 (Box 122)
    - Croce Rossa Americana 1918 (Box 122)
    - Dramatists' Guild 1928-1929 (Box 122)
    - Drexel Institute of Technology 1961 (Box 123)
    - Feltrinelli Award 1967-1968 (Box 123)
    - Harvard (Phi Beta Kappa) 1952 (Box 123)
    - National Institute of Arts and Letters 1937, 1957 (Box 123)
    - Northwestern University 1951, 2 folders (Box 123)
    - 100th anniversary commemoration (video by Townsend Ludington) 1996 (Box 123)
    - Pedro Franciso Award 1961 (Box 123)
    - Trieste commemoration memento 1967 (Box 124)
    - United States Navy Commendation (war correspondent) 1946 (Box 125)
    - Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government 1965-1966 (Box 125)
    - Virginia Library Foundation 1994 (Box 124)
    - World War I Verdun citation 1917 (Box 125)
    - World War II Asiatic-Pacific service ribbon (with ALS, General MacArthur) 1945 (Box 125)
    - Young Americans for Freedom n.d. (Box 125)
  - Diaries and notebooks (Box 125-126)
    - Bassano, Italy 1918-1919, 4 folders (Box 125)
    - Book of verses 1914-1917 (Box 125)
    - Europe 1911-1912, 2 folders (Box 125)
    - France and Italy 1917 (Box 125)
    - Literary diaries (2), vol. II 1914-1916 (Box 125)
    - Notebooks 1919-1927, n.d., 4 folders (Box 126)
    - Persian journey 1918, 1921[?] (Box 126)
    - Spain and France 1916-1917, n.d. (Box 126)
    - Venice, Greece and Constantinople 1921 (Box 126)
  - Memorabilia (Box 127-129)
    - Aba (worn on desert journey to Damascus) 1921-1922 (Box 127)
    - Affidavit by Dos Passos on Dr. William Horsley Gantt 1953 (Box 127)
    - Ambulance Corps discharge 1919, 1936 (Box 127)
    - Author's Guild membership 1970, n.d. (Box 127)
    - Bibliographical listing (writings of father, John Randolph Dos Passos) (Box 127)
    - Billfold with inserts ca. 1940-1947, n.d. (Box 127)
    - Calendars with John Dos Passos, Hemingway, Gerald Murphy images 1981, 1995 (Box 127)
    - Calling cards (John Dos Passos and miscellaneous) n.d. (Box 127)
    - Choate School and Harvard (student accounts) 1911, 1913 (Box 127)
    - Cinéma et Culture n.d. (Box 127)
    - Columbia University Law School Class Book (re: half brother, James Madison) 1896 (Box 127)
    - Date and address books 1940, n.d. (Box 127)
    - Draft registration certificate 1917 (Box 127)
    - Embroidered slipcase n.d. (Box 127)
    - Foreign stamps 1969-1970, n.d. (Box 127)
    - Genealogies (Dos Passos [in Portuguese] and Peyton families) n.d. (Box 127)
    - Hemingway/Dos Passos auto accident newsclip 1930 (Box 127)
    - Life magazine (correspondent documents) 1944-1945 (Box 127)
    - Lincoln's assassination report, New York Herald 1865 (Box 127)
    - Marvin, Walter Rumsey (his poem: "An Idyll") n.d. (Box 127)
    - Miscellany 1924-1946, n.d. (Box 127)
    - Murphy, Patrick F. [Gerald's father], (his diary) 1905 (Box 127)
    - Orient Express 1927 (Box 128)
      John Dos Passos autograph signed excerpt
    - Paper money (WWII mementos) 1944-1945 (Box 128)
    - Passports 1921-1938 (Box 128)
    - Picture post cards without notations n.d., ca. 445 items (4 folders) (Box 128)
    - Poster (Portuguese) with Dos Passos image 1963 (Box 128)
    - Pressed flower ("Mother's Rose") 1910 [1911?] (Box 129)
    - Recipe notes n.d. (Box 129)
    - School report card (Peterborough Lodge) 1906 (Box 129)
    - Soap bubble pistol invention n.d. (Box 129)
    - Travel memorabilia 1917-1919, n.d. (Box 129)
    - Volker Fund Grant application ca. 1958-1959 (Box 129)
    - War correspondent identification 1944 (Box 129)
    - War Risk Insurance policy 1918 (Box 129)
    - White House dinner mementos 1962 (Box 129)
    - Wilson, Edmund ("Bunny's lyrics") ca. 1933 (Box 129)
    - Zippo lighter 1956 (Box 129)
  - Personal data (Box 129)
    - Financial 1912-1965, n.d. (Box 129)
    - Legal 1949-1954 (Box 129)
    - Medical 1925-1943, n.d. (Box 129)
    - Property and household 1949, n.d. (Box 129)
  - Photographs (Box 130-133)
    - Ambulance Corps (WWI) 1917 (Box 130)
    - Arrested for picketing (Boston) 1927 (Box 130)
    - Brazil visits 1948-1963 (Box 130)
    - Childhood and youth 1896-ca. 1906, 2 folders (Box 130)
    - Chile 1969 (Box 130)
    - Choate School ca. 1907-1909, 1963 (Box 130)
    - Cummings, E.E. ca. 1961-1962 (Box 130)
    - Desert journey ca. 1921-1922 (Box 130)
    - Dos Passos family albums 1911-1912, 2 folders (Box 130-131)
    - Dos Passos family snapshots 1914-1980, n.d., 6 folders (Box 131)
    - Dos Passos, John Randolph (father), n.d. n.d., 2 folders (Box 131)
    - Dos Passo, Katharine (first wife) n.d. (Box 132)
    - Dos Passos, Lucy Addison Sprigg Madison (mother), 2 folders (Box 132)
    - Dos Passos, Lucy Cattell (paternal grandmother) n.d. (Box 132)
    - Farrell, James T. 1963 (Box 132)
    - Gaivota (father's yacht) n.d. (Box 132)
    - Harvard student ca. 1915-1916 (Box 132)
    - Holdridge, Larry and Barbara 1962 (Box 132)
    - International P.E.N. Club (conference in Japan) 1957 (Box 132)
    - Key West (with wife, Katy, and Canby Chambers) n.d. (Box 132)
    - Madison and Sprigg families 1859-1936, n.d. (Box 132)
    - Marriage to Elizabeth (Betty) Holdridge 1949 (Box 132)
    - Marvin, Walter Rumsey ("Rummy") 1920-1967 (Box 132)
    - Mexico 1926, 1972, n.d. (Box 132)
    - Miscellaneous 1980-1983 (Box 132)
    - Mitchell, Robert Stewart (Auk) 1916 (Box 132)
    - Murphy, Gerald and Sarah 1963 (Box 132)
    - Negatives file n.d. (Box 132)
    - Portraits of John Dos Passos 1921-1963, n.d. (Box 133)
    - Portugal visit 1967 (Box 133)
    - Provincetown (John Dos Passos, Katy, her brother, Bill, their homes and dog) ca. 1932-1942, n.d. (Box 133)
    - Sandy Point, Virginia n.d. (Box 133)
    - Skiing in Austria (with Hemingway and Gerald Murphy) 1926 (Box 133)
    - Spain visit 1967 (Box 133)
    - Spence's Point, Virginia home (John, Elizabeth, Lucy Dos Passos) ca. 1957-1970, n.d. (Box 133)
    - Steinbeck, John 1963 (Box 133)
    - Unidentified ca. 1900-1941, n.d. (Box 133)
    - War Correspondent service, ca. 1945 (Box 133)
    - White, William L. ca. 1960 (Box 133)
    - Wilson, Edmund ("Bunny") 1944 (Box 133)
  - Writings and reviews about Dos Passos (Box 134-139)
    - A Suggested Treatment of U.S.A./Anonymous (Box 134)
    - Die Literarische Entwicklung von John Dos Passos / by Werner Neuse 1931 (Box 134)
    - Dos Passos / by Lloyd B. Dennis 1964 (Box 134)
    - Dos Passos: A Reassessment / by Richard Hall 1970 (Box 134)
    - Dos Passos interview / by David Sanders 1969 (Box 134)
    - Dos Passos interview / by Frank Gado 1969 (Box 134)
    - Dos Passos--Writer's Days at Spencer's Point / by Suzanne H. Semsch 1982 (Box 134)
    - Dos, Which Side Are You On / by Dan Wakefield 1963 (Box 134)
    - Indicted with Theodore Dreiser/NY Herald Tribune article 1931 (Box 134)
    - John Dos Passos: Conservative Carping Critic 1991 (Box 134)
    - John Dos Passos: e a cidade dos homens vazios/Olympio Monat 1974 (Box 134)
    - John Dos Passos: Inventor in Isolation / by Alfred Kazin 1969 (Box 134)
    - John Dos Passos: Man of Esquire / by Toru Saito 1991 (Box 134)
    - John Dos Passos: reminiscências/Horizons U.S.A. (Box 134)
    - John Dos Passos: Swallowing America Whole/Playscript by Richard O. Moore 1981 (Box 134)
    - John Dos Passos: Writers in the Wilderness / by Margaret Marschall 1940 (Box 134)
    - La Influencia de Baroja en Dos Passos / by A.M. Vázqeuz Bigi 1968 (Box 134)
    - Lost Generation Journal/articles on war, Choate, journalism and morality 1977 (Box 134)
    - Obituaries of his death 1970 (Box 134)
    - Some Functions of Style in Dos Passos' U.S.A. / by S. A. Kamal 1972 (Box 135)
    - The Jazz Age [as reflected in John Dos Passos' writings] / by Marc Chenetier 1968 (Box 135)
    - The Literary Initiation of John Dos Passos / by Stephen Enniss 1994 (Box 135)
    - The Literary Lives of John Dos Passos / by Herbert Gold 1973 (Box 135)
    - Newsclips of Dos Passos and of his writings 1916-1997, n.d., 10 folders (Box 135-136)
    - The Odyssey of John Dos Passos/with William Hurt and Robert MacNeil 1994 (Box 136)
    - The Riddle of John Dos Passos / by Daniel Aaron 1962 (Box 136)
    - The Search for Identity in the Novels of Dos Passos / by Blanche H. Gelfant 1961 (Box 136)
    - Time magazine/cover story and recognition 1936, 1963 (Box 136)
    - Três Percursos Literários/Governo Regional Da Madeira ca. 1990 (Box 136)
    - U.S.A. / by Daniel Aaron 1996 (Box 137)
    - Um perfil e uma obra/Vida Mundial 1967 (Box 137)
    - Un Grande Affresco Degli Stati Uniti/Giuseppe Prezzolini 1965 (Box 137)
    - Unpublished writings on John Dos Passos / by C. W. Bernardin 1949, n.d., 16 folders (Box 137-139)
    - Untitled / by Robert Cantwell (Box 139)
    - Vita: John Dos Passos / by Pedro Beade 1993 (Box 139)
  Series IV
- Miscellaneous (Box 139-146)
  - Papers pertaining to other family members (Box 139-142)
    - Dos Passos, Elizabeth Holdridge (wife) 1953-1993, n.d., 3 folders (Box 139)
    - Dos Passos, John Randolph (father) 1880-1964, n.d., 7 folders (Box 139-140)
    - Dos Passos, Katharine (wife) 1922-1947, n.d., 6 folders (Box 140-141)
      w/Hemingway ALS
    - Dos Passos, Lucy Addison Sprigg Madison (mother) 1865-1913, 4 folders (Box 141-142)
    - Pifer, Ida (cousin) 1900-1902 (Box 142)
    - Smith, William Benjamin, Jr. (brother-in-law) 1925, n.d. (Box 142)
      w/Hemingway APC
    - Smith, William Benjamin, Sr. (father-in-law) 1891-1932, n.d., 3 folders (Box 142)
  - Papers pertaining to friends and associates (Box 143)
    - Bernardin, Charles W. 1911-1995, n.d. (Box 143)
    - McComb, Arthur 1919-1954, n.d. (Box 143)
    - McCormick, Wright 1915, n.d., 2 folders (Box 143)
    - Poore, Dudley 1915-1919, n.d. (Box 143)
  - Other writings and print matter (Box 143-144)
    - And Out Jumped the Fat Priest/anonymous (Box 143)
    - Assombrações Do Recife Velho / by Gilberto Freyre (Box 143)
    - Cape Cod Cooking/anonymous (Box 143)
    - Cardinal Merry del Val; A Folk Song of the Late 20th Century / by "Antipapist" (Box 143)
    - Court excerpt re: Sentencing of David Gordon 1927 (Box 143)
    - Dos I clap my hands and sing... (poem)/anonymous (Box 143)
    - Dos Passos: A Life / by Virginia Spencer Carr [publisher's promotion] 1984 (Box 143)
    - Feudeucias actuales de la poeme catalane (poem) / by Luis Jougeie 1920 (Box 143)
    - First American Novel (with ANS) / by Robert H. Elias 1941, 1959 (Box 143)
    - Liddell, Howard (on psychopathology, emotions and neurotic behavior) 1954-1957, n.d. (Box 143)
    - Neglected Passion / by Lucy Morse (Box 143)
    - Newsclips (miscellaneous) 1930-1966, n.d. (Box 143)
    - New Song for Indiana Ophelias / by Carl Sandberg [?] (Box 143)
    - Origin of the White Trash (article) (Box 143)
    - Paravism Diagnosed as a Disease of the Mind (article) 1917 (Box 143)
    - Professor Wigmore's Triumphal Tour / by Ernest Wigmore (Box 143)
    - Reminiscences of an 1805 visit with Joel Barlow / by Benjamin Silliman (Box 143)
    - Reminiscences of Lafcadio Hearn / by Setsuko Koizumi (Mrs. Hearn) (Box 143)
    - Reverie (poem)/anonymous 1919 (Box 143)
    - Rhythmical Science of the Universe (Box 143)
    - Riddle of Man's Ancestry / by W. L. Straus, Jr. 1949 (Box 144)
    - Sacco-Vanzetti Case / by Justice M. A. Musmanno 1963 (Box 144)
    - Sacco-Vanzetti: The End of the Chapter (article) 1970 (Box 144)
    - Short Stories by Edith Foley n.d., 2 folders (Box 144)
    - The Individual in the Modern World/Corning Conference Notes 1961, 2 folders (Box 144)
    - The Liberal, the Conservative, and the Pope / by Michael Novak 1964 (Box 144)
    - The Most Dangerous Man in Brazil / by Tito Leite[?] (Box 144)
    - The Secret of Good and Bad Luck (article) (Box 144)
    - The truth is generally a lie.. ./anonymous (Box 144)
    - To Marion, who asked for a Poem on a Day like this/anonymous (Box 144)
    - Un Sindicato Escolar / by Miguel Bustos Crecedo 1936 (Box 144)
    - Untitled [re: Dendry, Marion, and Melissa Cummings and Arthur]/anonymous (Box 144)
    - Untitled, unsigned/from Edith Shay ca. 1946 (Box 144)
    - Venom in the Treatment of Arthritis (Box 144)
    - Walking Dawn: A Recollection of Dawn Powell / by Rosalind Wilson (Box 144)
    - What shall I do with my dreams of you... / anonymous (Box 144)
    - Youth by Radiation / by Herman H. Rubin, MD 1924 (Box 144)
    - Collection control files [Restricted to Library Staff] (Box 145-147)
    - VIP Letters (Box 148)
      Letters by E. E. Cummings, Theodore Dreiser, F. Scott Fitzgerald, Zelda Fitzgerald, Ernest Hemingway, John F. Kennedy, H. R. Mencken, Henry Miller, Richard Nixon, and Upton Sinclair removed from other areas of the papers.